(
"ai_sub_version": "3.5.1",
"generated_at": "2026-08-10T21:26:57.300005",
"lyrics_prompt_version": 9,
"subtitles_prompt_version": 18,
"complete": true,
"max_retries_exceeded": false,
"any_pending": false,
"settings": (
"ai": (
"model": null,
"model_subtitles": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash-lite",
"model_lyrics": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash-lite",
"rpm": 4,
"tpm": 250000,
"google": (
"file_cache_ttl": 10,
"use_files_api": true,
"max_storage_gb": 18.0
),
"search": (
"qps": 0.3,
"max_length": 4096,
"web_search_tool": "langsearch",
"timeout": 60.0,
"retries": 3,
"min_wait_seconds": 1.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 10.0,
"multiplier": 2.0
),
"validation_buffer_ms": 2000,
"verification_gap_seconds": 60,
"gap_verification_retries": 1,
"gap_verification_ignore_start": true,
"gap_verification_ignore_end": true
),
"split": (
"max_seconds": 300,
"re_encode": (
"enabled": false,
"fps": 1.0,
"height": 360,
"bitrate_kb": 35,
"threshold_mb": 20,
"duration_tolerance_ms": 100,
"encoder": null
),
"start_offset_min": 0
"thread": (
"uploads": 4,
"re_encode": 2,
"lyrics": 4,
"subtitles": 4
),
"retry": (
"per_run": 5,
"max_runs": 3,
"multiplier": 2.0,
"min_wait_seconds": 30.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 300
),
"log": (
"level": "info",
"timestamps": true,
"scrub": false,
"progress_bars": true,
"progress_bar_width": 80,
"progress_bar_refresh_seconds": 1.0
)
言い訳ばかりまいて
Spreading excuses all around,
横切った未来 触れとうに くれないよう
so the passing future won't slip away unattained.
未知数が憧れに 絡まったって 奪えやしない
Even if unknowns entangle with my yearnings, they cannot be taken away.
空を創ろう
Let's create the sky!
散らかったパズル 組み合わせても 足りない
Even when combined, scattered puzzles are not enough.
壁に写した 知らない世界の 前にあった重い扉開け
Opening the heavy door that stood before a world unknown, projected on the wall,
忘れてた少年の 絵のように
like a painting of a forgotten boy—
温度は高く 微熱まじりで 夢はなしていたい
with high warmth and a hint of a slight fever, I want to keep dreaming.
もう憧れは 描きあくて 全部を見るため 空いたアトリエ
Yearning no more to just paint, an open atelier to see everything—
空いたアトリエ 帰るアトリエ いつかは
an open atelier, a returning atelier, someday...
想像して かきなぐって
Imagining and scribbling away,
塗り替えても 外はもっと 進んでいた
even when repainted, the outside world kept moving further ahead.
不揃いな 景色の中 棘が刺さっても 走ってみたい
Amidst a mismatched scenery, even if thorns pierce me, I want to try running.
道を創ろう
Let's create a path!
遠くなるほど 細く薄れて 描けない
The further away it gets, the thinner and fainter it becomes, impossible to draw.
イメージをした 近い未来 ぼやけたら 重い扉開け
Once I envisioned the near future and it blurred, I opened the heavy door,
その心 大胆に 染めよう
dyeing that heart boldly.
いつかの絵さえ 霞くらいの 夢生み出したい
I want to create dreams hazy enough to blur even paintings of the past.
成果なんてわからない きっと それでも 去ったアトリエ
Not knowing what the result will be, surely it's still the atelier I left behind.
ざっとアトリエ
Reaching my atelier...
僕のアトリエ
My atelier,
いつでも
anytime...
どれだけ濡れても
No matter how wet it gets,
擦ったって消えない
rubbing won't erase it.
戻せない
Reality cannot
現実は鮮やか
be undone; it's so vivid.
忘れてた少年の絵のように
Like a painting of a forgotten boy,
温度は高く
the temperature is high,
微熱まじりで夢話していたい
mixed with a slight fever, I want to dream.
もう憧れは描き飽きて
I'm tired of drawing my yearnings.
全部を見るため
To see everything,
開いたアトリエ
an open atelier—
an open atelier.
帰るアトリエ
Returning atelier,
いつかは
someday...
ふぅ…
Whew...
皆さんこんにちは！ホロライブ3期生の不知火フレアです！
Hello everyone! I'm Shiranui Flare from Hololive 3rd Generation!
今日は私の生誕祭ライブ2024にお越し下さり、皆さんありがとうございます！
Thank you all so much for coming to my Birthday Live 2024 today!
そんじゃって…見てくださいこのステージ！
And look at this stage!
すっごく可愛いでしょう！
Isn't it super cute?!
この日のために運営さんに作ってもらいました！本当にありがとうございます！
The management made this especially for this day! Thank you so much!
今日はこのステージでたくさん盛り上がっていくから、一緒にみんなで盛り上がろうね！
Today we're going to get super hyped on this stage, so let's get excited together everyone!
そして今日はゲストもたくさんいるので、ゲストのみんなともたくさん歌っちゃうよ！
And since we have lots of guests today, I'll be singing a lot with everyone too!
ハッシュタグはこちら、「不知火フレア生誕祭2024」でたくさんポストしてね！
The hashtag is here: #ShiranuiFlareBirthday2024, so please post a lot!
それでは今日はみんなでたくさん盛り上がっていきましょう！いくぞ！
Now then, let's all get super hyped today! Here we go!
ドクドクシテルコトバッカリアッパレスシタイアジワウミライ
Throbbing words only—praiseworthy, tasting the future!
サッパリスシタイアジワウミライ
Refreshing, tasting the future!
痛んだ小競り合いは 伸び切った舌戦なんか
Hurtful petty bickering and drawn-out verbal battles
飽きて匙を投げる そりゃ遠くに
I'm sick of and throw my spoon away, far into the distance.
巡り巡ってあなたのために掬う ああ スプーンにでもなれたらいいな
Circling around to scoop for you—ah, if I could just become a spoon!
絵に描いたご馳走じゃないのに フォンから作るソースじゃないのに ちょっとばっかなぜでしょう垂涎ものね
Though it's not a feast drawn in pictures, nor a sauce made from stock, somehow it's drool-worthy!
色鮮やかなサラダボウルに 好き嫌いも笑って試して 案外好きになってるじゃん
In a colorful salad bowl, laughing and trying likes and dislikes—turns out you've grown to like it!
鈍色の天気の日には 厚い雲を裂いていくような
On gloomy-colored days, like tearing through thick clouds,
風を見てみたい 魔法を見てみたい
I want to see the wind, I want to see magic!
思いつくだけのレシピを眺めて
Gazing at recipes just as I think of them,
振る舞おうぜ何回だって できたての料理を
I'll treat you as many times as you want to freshly made dishes!
満員の笑みが見られたのなら 創造の手間もどうだっていい
If I can see your full smile, the trouble of creation doesn't matter at all!
知らない巡り合わせは とんでもない未来
An unknown twist of fate leads to an extraordinary future—
分け合えると知るんだ 不揃いな皿でも 運命御馳走一杯 朝まで目いっぱい 話そう大小希望のプランを
realizing we can share even mismatched plates! A feast of destiny, eating our fill until morning, let's talk of big and small hopeful plans!
そうやって贅沢な匙を探していこう
That's how we'll search for a luxurious spoon.
ぬくもりも まどろみも
Both warmth and slumber
今日の最速で 飛んでく準備するから
I'll prepare to fly off with today's top speed,
連れてって欲しいのさ
so I want you to take me along!
朝日がよく見えるあの丘に
To that hill where the morning sun shines bright,
レジャーシートの用意も ブランケットの装備も すべてぱっと集めて揃ったよ 思い付きのキャンピングへ
leisure sheet ready, blanket equipped, I've gathered everything in a snap! Off to an impromptu camping trip!
誰でも巻き込み招待
Inviting and dragging anyone along!
思いっ切り期待が空ぶったとしても 理不尽ばっか襲ってきたって言いたくなっても
Even if expectations completely miss the mark, even if unreasonable things keep attacking and make me want to complain,
どうやったってダメな日もあるけど その失敗もスパイスなんだろう
there are days when nothing goes right no matter what, but even those failures must be the spice of life!
初めての料理がどんな苦くても 誇らしく思うんだ 傷テープ貼った手で やりきって精一杯
No matter how bitter my first dish turns out, I feel proud of it! With hands patched up with band-aids, I gave it my absolute all.
後悔しない失敗 明日にはそう思えるのかな
A failure with no regrets—I wonder if I'll be able to think that way tomorrow?
マダムダシラナイコトバッカリ
Madam, there are so many things I don't know!
ユックリイコウサンカンシタレ
Let's take it easy and participate!
ゆっくり行こう まったりしたい
Let's take it easy and relax.
単純に浸る好奇心
Pure curiosity to immerse myself in.
たっぷり満たそう
Let's fill ourselves up completely.
隣に居たい ささやかな気持ち秘めて
Wanting to stay by your side, hiding a small feeling...
少し怯えている不安な夜は
On nights when I feel a little scared and anxious,
弱い心照らすような 星を見ていたい 魔法を見てみたい
I want to see stars that light up a weak heart, I want to see magic.
思いつくだけのレシピを眺めて
Gazing at all the recipes I can think of,
振る舞おうぜ何回だってできたての料理を 満面の笑みが見られたのなら
Serving freshly made dishes over and over, if I can see your full smile.
創造の手間もどうだっていい 贅沢まで会えたとんでもない世界
No matter the hassle of creation, what an incredible world where we met in luxury!
食べ尽くしていくんだ酸いも甘いも全部 熱いままにいっぱい大好きなをいっぱい
Devouring everything, both bitter and sweet, piping hot and full of my favorites!
詰めよう大盛ご機嫌なメニューに
Let's pack it into a hearty, cheerful menu.
運命が小皿一杯 朝まで一杯 話そう大小希望のプランを
Fate in a small plate, a full cup until morning, let's talk about big and small plans of hope.
そうやって贅沢な日を探していこう
Let's keep searching for luxurious days like that.
愚かでいいのだろう
It's okay to be foolish,
身を浸す夢の跡
immersing myself in the remnants of dreams.
さようなら 藍き日々よ
Goodbye, blue days.
流れに身を任せ いつか大人になっていく
Letting the current take me, someday growing up...
少しずつ汚れていく事なの?
Is it about gradually getting dirty?
熟した果実だけ選ばれて
Only ripe fruits are chosen,
ナイフで裂かれて 呑み込まれる前に
sliced with a knife before being swallowed.
僕等は目指した Shangri-La
We aimed for Shangri-La,
欲望は抑えきれずに
unable to hold back our desires,
空想にまみれた 「自由」を求め続けた
wrapped in fantasies, we kept seeking "freedom."
今なら言えるだろう 此処がそう楽園さ
Now I can say it, this is paradise!
さようなら 藍き日々よ
Goodbye, blue days.
大切な何かを 踏み台にしてまでも
Even if it meant stepping on something precious,
一番高い林檎 掴みたかった
I wanted to grab the highest apple.
なくしてから気付く 尊いモノ
Realizing precious things only after losing them,
幼い僕等は 的はずれだらけさ
We were so off-target as kids.
満ち足りた日々の制裁は 感情不安定になる
The sanction of fulfilled days makes emotions unstable,
傷を負ってでも 羽ばたきたいと願うよ
Wishing to spread wings even if bearing scars.
愚かでいいのだろう 見渡す夢の痕
It's okay to be foolish, looking over the remnants of dreams.
さようなら 藍き日々よ
Goodbye, blue days.
輝く空は 無邪気を装い 全てを知っていた...
The shining sky feigned innocence and knew everything...
僕等は目指した Shangri-La
We aimed for Shangri-La...
欲望は...
Desires...
愚かでいいのだろう 見渡す夢の痕
It's okay to be foolish, looking over the remnants of dreams,
さよなら 蒼き日々よ
goodbye, blue days.
流れに身を任せ いつか大人になっていく
Letting the current take me, someday I'll grow up
少しずつ汚れていく事なのは？
and slowly get a little dirty...
熟した果実だけ 選ばれて
Only the ripe fruit gets chosen,
ナイフで裂かれて 飲み込まれる前に
sliced with a knife before being swallowed.
僕等は目指した Shangri-La
We aimed for Shangri-La.
欲求は抑えきれずに
Unable to control our desires,
空想にまみれた 「自由」を求め続けた
wrapped up in fantasies, we kept seeking freedom.
今なら言えるだろう 此処がそう楽園さ
Now I can say it, this is paradise.
さよなら 蒼き日々よ
Goodbye, blue days.
大切な何かを 踏み台にしてまでも
Even if it meant stepping on something precious,
一番高い林檎 掴みたかった
I wanted to grab the highest apple.
無くしてから気付く 尊いモノ
Realizing the precious things after losing them,
幼い僕等は 的はずれだらけさ
we were so off-target as kids.
満ち足りた日々の制圧は
The oppression of fulfilled days
感情不安定になる
makes us emotionally unstable.
傷を負ってでも 羽ばたきたいと願う
Even if we bear scars, we wish to spread our wings.
青のすみか作詞作曲：Tatsuya Kitani
[Song: Where Our Blue IsLyrics & Music: Tatsuya Kitani]
どこまでも続くような 青の季節は
In the season of blue that seemed to go on forever,
四つ並ぶ目の前を遮るものは 何もない
nothing obstructed the view of the four lined eyes.
アスファルト、蝉時雨を反射して
The asphalt ground reflected the chorus of cicadas,
君という沈黙が 聞こえなくなる
preventing me from hearing the silence of you.
この日々が 色褪せる
Those days faded away,
僕と違う君の匂いを知ってしまっても
even after I got to know your scent, different from mine.
置き忘れてきた永遠の底に
In the depths of eternity left behind,
今でも青が澱んでいる 今でも青が澄んでいる
our blue still lingers, our blue is still clear.
どんな祈りも言葉も 近づけるのに、届かなかった
No prayer or word could ever reach you, no matter how close they got.
まるで、静かな恋のような 頬を伝った夏のような色の中
Like a silent love, or a summer rolling down a cheek,
君を呪う言葉が ずっと喉の奥につかえている
I’ve got a curse word for you stuck in the back of my throat.
「また会えるよね」って 声にならない声
It is the unvoiced voice that says "We'll meet again, won't we?"
昼下がり、じりつく風の季節は
In the season of damp winds in the late afternoon,
想い馳せる、まだ何者でもなかった僕らの肖像
I think of the image of us who were still nobody.
何かも分かり合えたはずだった
We could have shared everything.
あの日から少しずつ 君と違う僕という呪いが肥えていく
Little by little since that day, the curse of me being different from you grew thicker.
(La-la-la-la, la-la-la-la)
君の笑顔の奥の憂いを見落としたこと、悔やみ尽くして
The sorrow behind your smile—all the way I've regretted missing it.
徒花と咲いて散っていく君に さよなら
To you, who bloomed and fell away as a fruitless flower, farewell.
今でも青が澱んでいる 今でも青が澄んでいる
Our blue still lingers, our blue is still clear.
どんな祈りも言葉も 近づけるのに、届かなかった
No prayer or word could ever reach you, no matter how close they got.
まるで、静かな恋のような 頬を伝った夏のような色の中
Like a silent love, or a summer rolling down a cheek,
君を呪う言葉が ずっと喉の奥につかえている
I've got a curse word for you stuck in the back of my throat.
「また会えるよね」って 声にならない声
It is the unvoiced voice that says "We'll meet again, won't we?"
無限に膨張する銀河の星の粒のように 指の隙間を零れた
Like star grains in an infinitely expanding galaxy, spilling through the gaps between my fingers.
越えて行こう 君と
Let's go beyond, together with you.
Soul salvation作詩：MEGUMI 作曲：たかはしごう
[Song: Soul salvationLyrics: MEGUMI / Music: Go Takahashi]
希望に溢れた未来 押し付けられている
A future flooded with hope is being forced upon us.
放り出された夢たちに 心が動けない
To the cast-aside dreams, my heart cannot move.
それでも前進めという 想いに導かれて
Even so, guided by the desire to push forward,
踏み出したその先 世界が変わる
The world beyond where I stepped out changes.
凍り付く氷を溶かせるものは 熱く燃え盛る魂
What can melt the freezing ice is a passionately burning soul.
眠らせていた まだ見ぬ力呼び起こせ
Awaken the unseen power that was slumbering!
大丈夫さ 繰り返す呟く 言葉は力生み出す
It's okay, repeating and whispering words create power.
其処底力には まだ先がある 突き抜けろ
From right here, there's still a ways to go, break through!
心の全力は 笑顔のため
The full strength of the heart is for smiles.
涙の向こう側を 超えて行ける 君と
I can go beyond the tears with you.
正しさを纏いながら 言葉の群れたちが
While maintaining righteousness, the flocks of words
勇気怪我傷を広げる 意識のないままに
bravely spread wounds, without any awareness.
それでもそこに 見えない愛 見つけられたとしたら
Even so, if we could find an invisible love there,
一つの光が世界を変える
A single light changes the world.
深い愛を 一瞬の姿を変えて 恨みの希望をむく
Changing deep love into a fleeting form, facing the hope of resentment.
裏切りがうむ 迷う心抱き締めて
Embrace the wavering heart born of betrayal.
培った友情を 些細な誤解で 傷をつけ合って
Cultivated friendships get hurt by trivial misunderstandings.
でも乗り越えて 絆となれば揺らがない
But once overcome, bonds become unshakable.
後悔があるから また歩ける
Because there are regrets, I can walk again.
雑音切り裂いて 超えて行こう 君と
Cut through the noise and let's go beyond, with you.
凍り付く氷を溶かせるものは 熱く燃え盛る魂
What can melt the freezing ice is a passionately burning soul.
眠らせていた まだ見ぬ力呼び起こせ
Awaken the unseen power that was slumbering!
大丈夫さ 繰り返す呟く 言葉は力生み出す
It's okay, repeating and whispering words create power.
其処底力には まだ先がある 突き抜けろ
From right here, there's still a ways to go, break through!
心の全力は 笑顔のため
The full strength of the heart is for smiles.
涙の向こう側を 超えて行ける 君と
I can go beyond the tears with you.
じっと日々を見逃さないで きっと大人ぶるらしくするので かかりきりになるんだ
Don't let days slip by fixedly, acting like grown-ups so we get absorbed.
話はまだ僕ら 真珠の欠片だって無価値 そこに物語がなければ
Our stories are worthless pearls if there's no tale within.
好き好きのような毎日を 当たり前に手をさしのべて少し知っている
Naturally reaching out hands to days like "I love you," knowing a little.
心温かであることは 笑うほど寂しいことはないでしょう
Being warm-hearted—surely nothing is as lonely as making you smile.
落ち込む夜で最低最悪で 気まぐれなように
On a depressed night, at your worst and most fickle,
どの人生も歩くはないだろう 強がることを知れど 今までの足跡 生まれたことは消えやしない
No life is impossible to walk; knowing how to act tough, the footsteps remain.
軽い冗談で傷がついてしまう 柔らかないたままでいい そのままでいい
A light joke leaves a scar, remaining soft and just as you are.
じっと日々を見逃さないで きっと大人ぶるらしくするので かかりきりになるんだ
Don't let days slip by fixedly, acting like grown-ups so we get absorbed.
話はまだ僕ら 真珠の欠片だって無価値 そこに物語がなければ
Our stories are worthless pearls without a tale inside...
からくりの中で回る僕らの血だ
Spinning within the clockwork, it's our blood.
間違ってないね
We aren't wrong, right?
劇ばかりじゃここには立っていないってこと
We wouldn't be standing here with just drama.
気晴らしに今ならどこへだって
For a distraction, right now, anywhere—
光のように気がつかない?
Can't you notice it like light?
間違ってる涙なんてない
There's no such thing as "wrong" tears.
じっと意味を見逃さないで きっと大人もそれらしく造るので
Don't let the meaning slip by; adults make it look convincing.
禍々リになるんだ 核心はまだ僕ら
Turning ominous, the core is still us.
真珠のかけらだって無価値 そこに物語がなければ
Even pearl fragments are worthless without a story.
からくりの中で回る僕らの血だ
Spinning within the clockwork, it's our blood.
じっと日日を見逃さないで きっと大人もそれらしく造るので
Don't let the days slip by; adults make it look convincing.
禍々リになるんだ 核心はまだ僕ら
Turning ominous, the core is still us.
真珠のかけらだって無価値 そこに物語がなければ
Even pearl fragments are worthless without a story.
からくりの中で回る僕らは
We, spinning within the clockwork...
成り損なってあふれた 走査線のような幸せを求めている
Seeking happiness like scan lines, overflowing from failure.
感情は絵の具 混ざり合うこの街で当たり前に今
In this town where emotions mix like paints, naturally right now
輝いている
they are shining.
ねえ 気づいて 大切な人は誰
Hey, realize it—who is the most precious person?
青い風が吹いた
A blue wind blew,
二つ影が並んだ
two shadows lined up side by side.
不器用なほどに揺ら揺ら揺れてた
Swaying so clumsily.
意識しないことで 自分自身守っては
Protecting yourself by not being conscious of it,
いつの日か光ったサインを眺めて
gazing at the sign that shines someday.
複雑に見せて 単純な恋なのに 答えが書かれたテストはまだ解けないんだ
Though it seems complex yet simple, the test with answers is still unsolved.
草を生やして ごまかしたって 心まではだませない
Even if you brush it off and fake it, you can't deceive your heart.
このままで言い訳ないよね 時は止まってくれないよ
There's no excuse left to stay like this; time won't stop for us.
素直になって 見つめ合えば 今までの曇り空を 青空へ
If we become honest and gaze at each other, the cloudy skies turn blue.
心どこかから結んだ虹が語る 二人を包み込んで 輝くよ
A rainbow woven from somewhere deep in our hearts shines, wrapping around us.
何気ないことがそう 替えがけないものへ
Things that seem trivial turn into something irreplaceable.
流れ行く雲の切れ目を探した
searching for a break in the passing clouds.
友達以上とか 恋人未満だとか
Like "more than friends" or "less than lovers"—
誰かが決めたルールを 飛び越えてみようよ
let's jump over the rules someone else decided!
意識し合って ありのままで 二人がもっと近づけば
If we're conscious of each other and just as we are, getting closer,
隠し続けてた鼓動はこの空に響いてくよ
the heartbeat we kept hidden will echo across this sky.
戸惑いだってい切なさだって その全てがきっと大切なもの
Confusion, pain—all of those are surely precious things.
二人に見えない 形のない思いを
Feelings without shape, invisible to the two of us—
手繰り寄せればきっと 引き合うよ
if we reel them in, surely we'll pull each other close.
当たり前の帰り道
The ordinary way home,
当たり前の連絡も
and the ordinary messages—
突然なくなるかもしれない
might suddenly disappear.
そっと心に手を当てて聞けばいい きっと
Just gently place your hand on your heart and listen, surely...
答えは一つだから
there is only one answer.
ねぇ 気づいて 大切な人は誰
Hey, realize it—who is the precious person?
嘘をついて ごまかしたって心まではだませない
Even if you lie and brush it off, you can't fool your heart.
眩しすぎるその光の中にふたりが見えるよ
In that dazzling light, I can see the two of us.
素直になって見つめ合えば今までの曇り空は青空へ
If we become honest and gaze at each other, the cloudy skies until now turn into a blue sky.
心と心結んだ虹がかかる
A rainbow connects our hearts.
ふたりを包み込んで輝くよ
It wraps around the two of us and shines bright.
はぁい、ということで……前半が終了しましたけど、みんな盛り上がってるー！
Haai, so... the first half has ended, but everyone, are you getting hyped?!
うん、今回のセットリストは前回よりも比較的新しい曲が多いななんて、思った？
Yeah, did you think that this setlist has relatively newer songs compared to last time?
え、ゲストとのお話とか、なんでこの曲を選んだのかな、とかは、え、そんな感じのお話はまた後日ゆっくりお話しできたらいいなと思っております。
Um, as for talks with guests and why I chose this song, um, I hope we can talk about things like that slowly at a later date.
え、この先もみんなが知っているあの曲やこの曲、え、ゲストもたくさんいるので、まだまだ一緒に盛り上がっていこうね！
Um, from here on too, there are songs everyone knows, and since there are lots of guests, let's keep getting hyped together!
あ、#不知火フレア生誕祭2024 でもまだまだ写真や感想どんどんポストしてくれたら嬉しいぞ！
Ah, I'd be happy if you keep posting photos and impressions with #不知火フレア生誕祭2024!
それでは、後半戦に行きましょう！ ぐーぐーぐーぐー！
Now then, let's head into the second half! Gu-gu-gu-gu!
春泥棒 作詞作曲：n-buna
Haru Dorobou / Lyrics & Music: n-buna
高架橋を抜けたら
As I crossed over the bridge,
雲の隙間に青が覗いた
I could see the blue sky peeking through the clouds.
最近どうも暑いから
It's been really hot lately,
ただ風が吹くのを待ってた
so I was just waiting for the wind to blow.
木陰に座る
Sitting in the shade of a tree,
何か頬に付く
something gets stuck to my cheek.
見上げれば頭上に咲いて散る
Looking up, flowers bloom and scatter overhead.
はらり、僕らもう息も忘れて
Falling softly, we've already forgotten to breathe,
瞬きさえ億劫
even blinking is too much trouble.
さあ、今日さえ明日 過去に変わる ただ風を待つ
Now, even today turns into yesterday's past, just waiting for the wind.
だから僕らもう声も忘れて さよならさえ億劫
That's why we've already forgotten our voices, even goodbyes are too much trouble,
ただ花が降るだけ 晴れ、今、春吹雪
petals just fall down under the clear sky—now, a spring blizzard.
次の日も待ち合わせ
Meeting up again the next day,
花見の客も少なくなった
the cherry blossom viewers have also decreased.
春の匂いはもう止む
The scent of spring is already stopping.
今年も夏が来るのか
Will summer come again this year?
高架橋を抜けたら
As I crossed over the bridge,
道の先に君が覗いた
I could see you peeking out at the end of the path.
残りはどれだけかな どれだけ春に会えるだろう
How much time is left, I wonder? How many more springs will I be able to see?
川沿いの丘、木陰に座る
On the hill along the river, sitting beneath the shade of a tree...
また昨日と変わらず今日も咲く
Blooming today, just like yesterday.
花に、僕らもう息も忘れて
Amidst the flowers, we forget to even breathe,
瞬きさえ億劫
finding even blinking too much trouble.
花散らせ今 吹くこの嵐は
Scatter the blossoms now, this storm blowing through
まさに春泥棒
is truly a spring thief.
風に今日ももう時が流れて
Time flows on with the wind today as well,
立つことさえ億劫
making even standing up too much trouble.
花の隙間に空、
The sky peers through the gaps in the flowers,
散れり まだ 春吹雪
still scattering in a spring snowstorm.
今日も会いにいく
I'm going to see you again today.
木陰に座る
Sitting in the shade of the trees,
溜息を吐く
I let out a sigh.
花ももう終わる
The flowers are almost done,
明日も会いにいく
I'll go see them tomorrow too.
春がもう終わる
Spring is almost over,
名残るように時間が散っていく
and time scatters as if reluctant to leave.
愛を歌えば言葉足らず
Sing of love and words fall short,
踏む韻さえ億劫
leaving even rhyming too much trouble.
花開いた今を 言葉如きが語れるものか
Can mere words ever capture the present when flowers bloom?
はらり、僕らもう声も忘れて
Gently, we forget our voices too,
瞬きさえ億劫
finding even blinking too much trouble.
花見は僕らだけ
We're the only ones viewing the blossoms,
散るな まだ 春吹雪
don't fall yet, spring snowstorm.
あともう少しだけ
Just a little longer,
もう数えられるだけ
just enough to count them.
あと花二つだけ もう花一つだけ
Just two flowers left, just one flower left,
もう花一つだけ
just one more flower left,
ただ葉が残るだけ
leaving only leaves behind.
今、はらり 春仕舞い
Now, gently, bidding farewell to spring.
君が持ってきた漫画 くれた知らない名前の花
The manga you brought, the flower with the unknown name you gave me.
今日はまだ来ないかな 初めての感情知ってしまった
Wonder if today won't come yet? I've come to know a brand new emotion.
窓に飾った絵画をなぞって ひとりで宇宙を旅して 君の手を握ってしまったら 孤独を知らないこの街には もう二度と帰ってくることは
Tracing the painting on the window, traveling the universe alone... if I had taken your hand, to this town that knows no loneliness, I could never return again.
君が手を差し伸べた 光で影が生まれる 歌って聞かせて この話の続き
You reached out your hand, light creating shadow. Sing and let me hear the rest of this story,
連れて行って 見たことない星まで
take me away to a star I've never seen before.
誰の手も声も届かない 高く聳え立った塔の上へ
To the top of a tower standing tall where no hands or voices reach,
飛び出すフウセンカズラ 僕は君に笑って欲しいんだ
balloon vine taking flight, I just want you to smile.
歌って聞かせて この話の続き 連れて行って 見たことない星まで
Sing and let me hear the rest of this story, take me away to a star I've never seen before.
誰も手も声も届かない 高くそびえ立ったその上で
High atop that tower where no one's hands or voices can reach,
飛ばす風船風だ 僕は君に笑って欲しかった
letting loose balloons—I just wanted you to smile.
満たされない穴は 惰性の会話や 澄ましたポーズで これまでは埋めてきたけど
Unfilled voids, casual conversations, and composed poses—I've filled them all this time, but...
退屈な日々を蹴散らして 君と二人で この街中を泳いだら 素敵なことでしょう
scattering these tedious days, if the two of us could swim through this town together, wouldn't that be wonderful?
君が持ってきた漫画 くれて知らない名前のお花
The manga you brought, the flower with an unknown name you gave me
今日はまだ来ないかな?
Won't you come today either?
初めての感情 知ってしまった
I've come to know emotions for the first time
窓に飾った絵画をなぞって ひとりで宇宙を旅して
Tracing the paintings decorated on the window, traveling alone through the universe
君の手を握ってしまったら
If I were to hold your hand
孤独を知らないこの街には もう二度と帰ってくることは
To this town that knows no loneliness, I'll probably never be able to return again
君が手を差し伸べた 光で影が生まれる
A shadow is born from the light you reached out with
歌って聞かせて この話の続き
Sing and let me hear the continuation of this story
連れて行って 見たことがない星まで
Take me away to a star I've never seen before
誰の手も声も届かない 高く聳え立った塔の上へ 飛ばすフウセンカズラ
Where no one's hands or voices can reach, to the top of the towering tower, flying balloon vine
僕は君に笑って欲しいんだ
I want you to smile
満たされない穴は 惰性の会話や
Unfilled holes used to be filled with idle conversation
澄ませたポーズで これまでは埋めてきたけど
and smug poses...
退屈な日々を蹴散らして
Scattering these boring days
君と二人で この街中を泳いできたら素敵でしょう?
If the two of us could swim through this town, wouldn't that be wonderful?
出したこともないほど 大きな声でやっと君に伝わる
With a voice louder than ever before, I finally reach you
歪なくらいがさ 世界の端と端を結んで
Even a little distortion is surely just right, connecting the edges of the world
窓に飾った絵画をなぞって ひとりで宇宙を旅して
Tracing the paintings decorated on the window, traveling alone through the universe
それだけでも不自由じゃないけど 僕は選んでみたいの
Even without that, I'd be free, but I want to choose
高鳴る心臓だらけの空を
a throbbing heart and a sky full of mysteries
安全なループを今書き換えて
Rewrite the safe loop now
It’s only love
もしもし願い一つだけ叶うなら
If I am granted only one of my wishes
君の側で眠らせて
Let me sleep by your side
どんな場所でもいいよ
anywhere is okay
Beautiful world
迷わず君だけを見つめている
Without losing sight, I am looking only at you
Beautiful boy
自分の美しさまだ知らないの
You still don't know your own beauty
It’s only love
寝ても覚めても少年マンガ 夢見てばっかり
Whether I am asleep or awake, I simply dream of boy's manga
自分が好きじゃないの
You don't like yourself
何が欲しいか分からなくて ただ欲しがって
Not knowing what I want, I still can't help wanting
ぬるい涙が頬を伝う
Tepid tears run down my cheeks
言いたいことなんかない
I have nothing I want to say
ただもう一度会いたい
All I want is to see you again
言いたいこと言えない 根性無しかもしれない
I can't say what I want to say, maybe I am a coward
それでいいけど もしもし願い一つだけ叶うなら
But that's fine. If I am granted only one of my wishes
君の側で眠らせて
Let me sleep by your side
どんな場所でもいいよ
anywhere is okay
Beautiful world
迷わず君だけを見つめている
Without losing sight, I am looking only at you
Beautiful boy
自分の美しさまだ知らないの
You still don't know your own beauty
It’s only love
どんなことでもやってみて 損をしたって少し経験値上がる
You try to do everything, even though you may lose something, it will be a good experience
新聞なんかいらない 肝なことが載ってないの
I don't need newspapers, there's nothing important in them
It's only love
もしも願い一つだけ 叶うなら
If I am granted only one wish,
君の側で眠らせて
let me sleep by your side.
どんな場所でもいいよ
Anywhere is fine.
Beautiful world
迷わず君だけを見つめている
Without hesitating, I'm looking only at you.
Beautiful boy
自身の美しさ まだ知らないの
You still don't know your own beauty.
It's only love
寝ても覚めても少年マンガ 夢見てばっかり
Whether asleep or awake, I just dream of boy's manga.
自分が好きじゃないの
You don't like yourself.
何が欲しいか 分からなくて ただ欲しがって
Not knowing what you want, just wanting it,
ぬるい涙が頬を伝う
tepid tears run down your cheeks.
言いたいことなんかない
I have nothing I want to say,
ただもう一度会いたい
I just want to see you once more.
言いたいこと言えない
I can't say what I want to say,
根性無しかもしれない
maybe I'm a coward.
それでいいけど
But that's fine.
もしも願い一つだけ 叶うなら
If I am granted only one wish,
君の側で眠らせて
let me sleep by your side.
どんな場所でもいいよ
Anywhere is fine.
Beautiful world
迷わず君だけを見つめている
Without hesitating, I'm looking only at you.
Beautiful boy
自身の美しさ まだ知らないの
You still don't know your own beauty.
It's only love
どんなことでもやってみて 損をしたって 少し経験値上がる
Try doing anything, even if you lose something, your experience goes up a bit.
ニュースなんかいらない 肝心なことが載ってない
I don't need the news, nothing important is in it.
最近調子どうだい? 元気にしてるなら 別にいいけど
How's it going lately? If you're doing fine, that's okay, I guess.
僕の世界消えるまで 会えるなら 君の側で眠らせて どんな場所でも結構
Until my world disappears, if I can meet you, let me sleep by your side, any place will do.
Beautiful world
僅か過ぎて行く日々の中で
In the fleeting days that pass by,
Beautiful boy
気分のムラは仕方ないね
there's nothing we can do about our shifting moods.
もしも願い一つだけ 叶うなら
If I am granted only one wish,
君の側で眠らせて
let me sleep by your side.
どんな場所でもいいよ
Anywhere is fine.
Beautiful world
迷わず君だけを見つめている
Without hesitating, I'm looking only at you.
Beautiful boy
自身の美しさ まだ知らないの
You still don't know your own beauty.
It's only love
Beautiful world
(Question 大胆に演じて)
(Question: Act boldly)
(Question 他愛のない人生)
(Question: A life of triviality)
(Question 背反と安寧)
(Question: Antithesis and peace)
(Question What? ×××××)
(Question: What? XXXXX)
真っ二つだね世界は 隠したそれぞれの正義は
The world is split right in half, and our hidden forms of justice
抵抗するがらんどう ダマになり重なって
Stand at a stalemate, hollow shells piling up and clustering together
(Two-Sided Two-Face)
常識 劣勢 裏の裏
Conventional wisdom, inferiority, the reverse of the reverse
最後も最期も関係ない
Neither the end nor the very end matters anymore
間一髪がスタンダード どうにかしてきたんだ
A hair's breadth away is the standard, and we've managed to get this far
狂ったストーリー 全てが決まってたように
A crazy story, as if everything was predetermined
のべつ幕無しに異常事態 大抵わけもない
Ceaseless abnormal situations, usually for no real reason
正しい間違いが不安定で 裏返しの本音が溜まってゆく
Right and wrong are unstable, and our reversed true feelings pile up
消化する術がないことも 気付かずに立ち向かうのか?
Are you going to keep facing forward without even realizing that you have no way to digest it all?
悲しくなどないけど こんなんじゃまだ100%は分からない
It's not like I'm sad, but like this, I still don't understand 100%
もう不安など消してしまえたら良いと願って望んで憂い
I wish and hope and fret that I could just erase all my anxiety
そのカーテンが翻ったなら って理想と現実揺らぐんだ
When that curtain flutters, ideals and reality waver
クラクラ
Dizzy
身一つで生き抜いた 土砂降りに固まる不平不満
Surviving with just my own body, complaints and grudges solidifying in the downpour
逆行する世界も たまに味方となって
Even a world moving in reverse sometimes becomes an ally
(Two-Sided Two-Face)
正義で 正義に抗うの?
Are you going to rebel against justice with justice?
サイコロ振っても平行線
Even if you roll the dice, it's parallel lines
どうして? なんで世界は ドラマみたいにいかないのだろう
Why? Why doesn't the world go smoothly like a drama?
(Question 大胆に演じて)
(Question: Act boldly)
冴えないジョークで笑えたあの頃のように
Just like those days when we could laugh at a lame joke
特別はいつも目の前にある 大抵わけもない日常
Specialness is always right in front of us, in our usually uneventful daily lives
日常
daily lives
寂しい言葉がフラッシュバックしてる
Lonesome words are flashing back.
泣いてしまえたら楽だったかな
Would it have been easier if I had just cried?
どっちつかずで嫌になるな
I hate being stuck in the middle.
守りたいものは何？
What is it that I want to protect?
知らないことばっかだこんなんじゃまだ
There's so much I don't know, this isn't enough yet.
1％にも満たないって悩んで
Worrying over not even reaching 1%,
学んで繰り返し 少しずつ見えてきた未来
learning, repeating, a future gradually coming into view.
正しい間違いが不安定で 裏返しの本音が溜まってゆく
Right and wrong are unstable, and my hidden true feelings pile up.
消化する術がないことも 気付かずに立ち向かうの？
Am I going to face it without realizing I have no way to digest it?
悲しくなどないけどこんなんじゃまだ
I'm not sad, but this isn't enough yet.
100％は分からないもう不安など
I don't know 100%, if only I could erase all anxiety.
消してしまえたら良いと願って望んで
Wishing and hoping for it.
そのカーテンが翻ったなら って理想と現実揺らぐんだ
If that curtain flips over, my ideals and reality waver.
クラクラ
Kura kura...
はーいみんな楽しんでますかー！
Hii, are you all enjoying yourselves?!
ついに残す曲はあと1曲となりましたが、その前にここで一度、自分宣伝いいですか？
Finally, we're down to just one song left, but before that, can I do a little self-promotion here?
あーなんかこの空気 新曲発表みたいな空気になっちゃうかなと思うんですけど、あの大変恐縮なのですが、今回はなんと……違います！笑
Ah, I feel like this atmosphere is turning into one where I'm announcing a new song, but um, I'm terribly sorry, this time... that's not it! Haha.
いやじゃあなんで今宣伝ないんやってとこなんですけど、
Well, you might wonder why I'm doing promotion right now, but...
いや、なんていうか、うーん最後はエモい感じで終わらせたいんだもん！
well, how should I put it? Hmm, I just want to end on an emotional note!
ということでお約束、グッズ紹介！
So as promised, merchandise introduction!
もちろん今年も出します！不知火フレア誕生日記念グッズ2024！
Of course I'm releasing them this year too! Shiranui Flare Birthday Celebration Goods 2024!
まずはこちら！「おうちでまったりアクリルジオラマスタンド」！
First is this! The "Relaxing at Home Acrylic Diorama Stand"!
イラストはちょん先生に描いていただきました！ありがとうございます！
The illustration was drawn by Chon-sensei! Thank you very much!
おうちで一緒にまったり過ごす雰囲気が可愛くて和んじゃう！君も一緒にゲームしない？
The cozy vibe of relaxing together at home is so cute and heartwarming! Won't you play games with me too?
続いてはこちら！「ランダムマルチバンド」！イラストは染谷うるは先生に描き下ろしていただきました！
Next is this! The "Random Multi-Band"! Illustrations were newly drawn by Someya Uruha-sensei!
いつもありがとうございます！長くて気になるコードなんかを私がまとめちゃうぞ！衣装も4種類！どれも私もちゅきすぎ！
Thank you as always! I'll bundle up those long, bothersome cords for you! 4 outfit variations too! I love every single one of them!
そして、フレアとおでかけぬいぐるみ おでかけ衣装ver. フレアも外に連れてって、なんちゃって、少し小さめの縫いも欲しいなんて要望にお答えしてみました！おでかけ衣装のかわいい私とおでかけしない？
And, the "Flare Out-and-About Plushie (Out-and-About Outfit ver.)". Taking Flare outside, just kidding, we answered requests for wanting a slightly smaller plushie too! Won't you go out with cute me in my outing outfit?
最後はこちら！フレアとおそろいジャージ！く、黒が着やすい、なんてみんなの意見にきゅ、屈しました！うーん、黒もいいじゃん！私とおそろいでちょっとそこのコンビニまでデートしない？ワンポイントで隠れ推しアピールも可愛いぞ！フルセット購入はこちら！めちゃくちゃ可愛い！ちょん先生描き下ろしポストカードがついてくるよ！
Last is this! The "Flare Matching Jersey!" I y-yielded to everyone's opinions that b-black is easy to wear! Hmm, black looks good too! Won't you go on a date with me in matching outfits down to the convenience store nearby? The subtle one-point oshi appeal is also cute! Purchase the full set here! Super cute! It comes with a newly drawn postcard by Chon-sensei!
そして今回も書きます！数量限定直筆メッセージ！数量限定だけどいつもよりかなり量増やしたので焦らず慌てずみんなの手にわたるかも！複製メッセージの方も今回も少しだけ長めに書くから万が一買えなかったって人も悲しまないでね！
And I'll write them this time too! Quantity-limited handwritten messages! It's limited in quantity, but I increased the volume quite a bit compared usual, so don't rush or panic, it might reach everyone's hands! For the duplicated message version, I'll write a bit longer this time too, so please don't be sad if by any chance you couldn't buy one!
改めて今日はみんな来てくれてありがとうございました！ついに最後の曲となりました！君たちに出会えて本当に良かった！みんな大好きだよ！
Once again, thank you everyone for coming today! Finally, it's our last song! I'm so truly glad I met you all! I love you all so much!
遠くで遠くで揺れてる稲穂の海 帆を上げ帆を上げ目指した思い出へと
Far, far away, a sea of swaying rice ears. Raising our sails, raising our sails toward the memories we aimed for.
僕らは今日までの悲しいこと全部覚えてるか、忘れたか
Do we remember all the sad things up until today, or have we forgotten them?
小さな手にもいつからか僕ら追い越してく強さ
Someday, even in the palm of a tiny hand, there will be strength to surpass us.
遠く遠くで揺れてる稲穂の海
Far, far away, a sea of swaying rice ears
帆を上げ帆を上げ目指した思い出へと
Raising our sails, we headed toward the memories we aimed for
僕らは今日までの
Everything up until today...
悲しいこと全部
all the sad things,
覚えているか
do we remember them,
忘れたか
or have we forgotten?
小さな手にも いつからか
Even in the palm of a tiny hand,
僕ら追い越して
someday surpassing us,
熟れた葡萄の下 泣いていた日から
we walked from the days when we cried
歩いた
beneath the ripe grapes.
小さな手でも 離れても
Even if our hands are small, even if we're separated,
僕らはこの道ゆくんだ
we'll go on this road.
いつかくる日は 一番の
Until that day in the future
思い出を仕舞って
we will cherish our memories.
季節は移り もう冷たい風が
The seasons change and the cold wind
包まれて眠れ あの春の歌の中で
has already wrapped and sleeping in the song of that spring.
あの春の歌の中で
In the song of that spring...
小さな手にも いつからか
Even in the palm of a tiny hand,
僕ら追い越して
someday surpassing us,
濡れた頬には どれだけの
how many smiles
笑顔が映った
reflected on our wet cheeks?
小さな手でも 離れても
Even if our hands are small, even if we're separated,
僕らはこの道ゆくんだ
we'll go on this road.
そしてくる日は 僕らの
And on the day that comes
思い出を仕舞った
we put away our memories.
小さな手でも いつ日の日か
Some day the palm of a tiny hand
僕ら追い越してゆくんだ
will go over us.
やがてくる日は 新しい季節を
The day that finally came opened
開いた
a new season.